## Luca Di Stefano

Curriculum vitae March 2022

## Personal information

E-mail: luca.di-stefano@inria.fr

Work address: 655 avenue de l'Europe, 38334 Montbonnot, France

**Web page:** convecs.inria.fr/people/Luca.Di-Stefano/

## Research interests

My research mainly concerns the formal modelling and analysis of agent-based models of complex collective systems. On one hand, this entails the development of formally defined high-level languages to concisely describe the features of individual agents; on the other hand, it requires applying and improving state-of-the-art verification techniques to check the collective behaviour of the resulting system.

Keywords associated with my interests include:

**Modelling**: Agent-based modelling, Attribute-based communication, Collective adaptive systems, Domain-specific languages, Multi-agent systems, Process algebras, Stigmergic interaction, Structural operational semantics, Temporal logics.

**Analysis**: Bounded model checking, Explicit-state and symbolic model checking, Software verification, Static analysis.

### **Education**

#### **Gran Sasso Science Institute**

L'Aquila, Italy

PhD in Computer Science November 2016 – October 2020

**Thesis**: Modelling and Verification of Multi-Agent Systems via Sequential Emulation

**Advisors**: Rocco De Nicola, Omar Inverso **URL**: hdl.handle.net/20.500.12571/10181

Other activities: Student representative in the academic senate (2018–2020).

#### University of L'Aquila

L'Aquila, Italy

MSc in Computer Science and Systems Engineering March 2014 – October 2016 **Thesis**: Design of a reactive system for autonomous UAV navigation in unknown environments. Thesis written in Italian. Original title: *Progettazione di un sistema reattivo per la navigazione autonoma di un drone in ambienti sconosciuti*.

Advisors: Eliseo Clementini, Enrico Stagnini

Final grade: 110/110, cum laude

Official degree name: Ingegneria Informatica e Automatica.

# Positions held

### CONVECS, Inria/LIG

Grenoble, France

Post-doctoral researcher

November 2020 – Present time

The aim of this post-doc is to enable efficient model checking of temporal properties in the context of collective adaptive systems. Building upon previous work with the CONVECS team, I developed an automated translation of a state-based temporal property language into MCL (an extension of the alternation-free fragment of the modal  $\mu$ -calculus), and used it to verify a selection of systems. I am also investigating how compositional verification techniques may help with model checking of large systems.

## SySMA, IMT Lucca

Lucca, Italy

Grant holder

December 2019 – October 2020

The grant topic was "Verification of Emerging Properties in Collective Adaptive Systems". I adapted a structural encoding procedure I had been working upon as part of my PhD to multiple verification tools implementing a variety of techniques, including predicate abstraction, *k*-induction and property-directed reachability.

#### CONVECS, Inria/LIG

Grenoble, France

Visiting PhD student

March – July 2019

As a visitor at CONVECS I focussed on topics related to my thesis, such as defining a structural encoding of multi-agent systems in the LNT specification language and using it to verify these systems through model checking.

# **Teaching**

### **Polytech Paris-Saclay**

Paris, France

MSc course in Modelling and Verification

April – May 2021

36-hour course for Master students in Computer Science Engineering, *filière apprentissage*. Held remotely as a supply teacher (*intervenant vacataire*). The course focused on the following topics: modelling of concurrent systems through communicating automata (labelled transition systems); behavioural equivalences; process algebras (CCS, LNT); modal and temporal logics (HML,  $\mu$ -calculus, MCL); model checking; modelling of real-time systems through timed automata; model-based testing. Tools such as CADP and UPPAAL were showcased in lab sessions.

## Other academic activities

## Reviewing activity.....

I have served as a reviewer or sub-reviewer for the following conferences and journals:

- International Conference on Autonomous Agents and Multiagent Systems (AAMAS)
- International Symposium on Formal Methods (FM)
- International Conference on Formal Techniques for Distributed Objects, Components, and Systems (FORTE)
- International Conference on Software Technologies (ICSOFT)

- International Conference on Software Engineering and Formal Methods (SEFM)
- o Science of Computer Programming, Elsevier
- Theoretical Aspects of Software Engineering Conference (TASE)

# Participation to PhD schools

### 1st VMCAI Winter School

Lisbon, Portugal

January 2019

The school featured lectures on several topics associated with the VMCAI conference series, including: abstract interpretation (Patrick Cousot, New York University); computing with SAT oracles (João Marques-Silva, University of Lisbon); neural network verification (M. Pawan Kumar, University of Oxford); verification of distributed protocols (Ken McMillan, Microsoft Research).

## Invited presentations.....

- Verifying collective adaptive systems by emulation. Remote presentation to the Formal Methods unit of the Computer Science and Engineering department at Chalmers Institute. Gothenburg, Sweden, 10 March 2022.
- o *Multi-agent* (*smart*) *systems with virtual stigmergies*. Kickoff meeting of Italian national research project (PRIN) *IT MATTERS: Methods and Tools for Trustworthy Smart Systems*. Pisa, Italy, 14 October 2019.
- o *Multi-agent systems with virtual stigmergies*. Invited presentation at IMT School for Advanced Studies. Lucca, Italy, 3 July 2018.

### Skills

**Technical skills**: My experience in programming spans more than a decade. As of now my languages of choice are mainly F# and Python, but I have worked with a number of popular languages across the years (e.g., C, C++, C#, Erlang, Go, Java, Prolog). I have some knowledge of control theory, computer architectures, assembly languages, and hardware description languages (mainly VHDL). I am also familiar with version control systems such as Git and Subversion.

**Language skills**: Italian is my first language. I am fluent in English (CEFR level C1–C2) and have some knowledge of French (CEFR level A2–B1).

**Soft skills**: Having been the main contributor to all my publications so far, I have acquired good academic writing skills, as well as an ability to work in groups, meet deadlines, and present my ideas both to my team mates and to external audiences.

# **Publications**

# Journal articles.....

Luca Di Stefano, Rocco De Nicola, and Omar Inverso. 2022. "Verification of Distributed Systems via Sequential Emulation". In: *TOSEM* 31.

Rocco De Nicola, Luca Di Stefano, and Omar Inverso. 2020. "Multi-Agent Systems with Virtual Stigmergy". In: *Sci. Comput. Program.* 187.

Rocco De Nicola, Luca Di Stefano, and Omar Inverso. 2018. "Toward Formal Models and Languages for Verifiable Multi-Robot Systems". In: *Front. Robot. AI* 5.

# Peer-reviewed conference and workshop papers.....

Luca Di Stefano and Frédéric Lang. 2021. "Verifying temporal properties of stigmergic collective systems using CADP". In: *ISoLA*.

Luca Di Stefano, Frédéric Lang, and Wendelin Serwe. 2020. "Combining SLiVER with CADP to Analyze Multi-agent Systems". In: *COORDINA-TION*.

Rocco De Nicola, Luca Di Stefano, and Omar Inverso. 2018. "Multi-Agent Systems with Virtual Stigmergy". In: *STAF Workshops*.

# Citation indices.....

Accessed on Scopus on March 9, 2022.

Citations: 16

h-index: 3